<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sermons of Barnardine Ochine of Sena godlie, frutefull, and uery necessarye for all true Christians translated out of Italien into Englishe</title>
            <author>Ochino, Bernardino, 1487-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837257</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837257</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1572</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1572)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 997:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sermons of Barnardine Ochine of Sena godlie, frutefull, and uery necessarye for all true Christians translated out of Italien into Englishe</title>
                  <author>Ochino, Bernardino, 1487-1564.</author>
                  <author>Bacon, Anne Cooke, Lady, 1528?-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Carr for W. Redell],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Do. M.D.XLVIII [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Five sermons.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by Lady Anne Bacon, of the Italian original.</note>
                  <note>"STC lists this as another edition of the 1548 Ipswich collection of sermons translated by Richard Argentine. it is, however, an entirely different work, the translator of which is unidentified."--NUC Pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Title page marked, torn and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, Italian --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1572:1"/>
            <p>SERMONS OF BARNARDINE OCHINE OF SENA GODLYE, frutefull, and uery neceſſarye for all true Chriſtians tranſlated out of Italien into Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>ANNO DO. M.D.XLVIII. <hi>Menſis Iulio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1572:2"/>
            <head>The contentes of thys booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>i How a Chriſty an oughte to make hys laſt wyll and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</item>
               <item>ii How we ſhuld anſwere the deueil, when he tempteth vs and namely in the ende of our lyfe.</item>
               <item>iii How anſwere is to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de at the iudgement ſeate of god.</item>
               <item>iiii By what meane to come to heauen.</item>
               <item>v How god hath ſatiſfyed for our ſynnes and hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſyd Paradice for vs.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1572:2"/>
            <head>THE INTERPRETOVR TO <hi>the gentle reader healthe in Chriſte Ieſu.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>DEATH (GOOD READER) <hi>as ſcripture declareth, and our dayly</hi>
               </hi> experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce practeſeth, to all mankynde is a thing moſt certeine and ſure. For who is he that ſhall lyue &amp; not ſe nor taſt of deathes cuppe: the longeſt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers at length dyed, neytherkyng ne keyſar can auoyde the duyte of death, but of neceſſitie, as al are of earth and aſſhes, ſo ſhall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into the ſame.</p>
            <p>Notwythſtandynge thys that ſure we be to dye, yet when it ſhall come, the Lord hath lefte ſecret to hys owne wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, chefelye bycauſe we ſhulde euer kepe watche, and warde, &amp; be ſtyll in aredines wyth our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes burnyng to wayte vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1572:3"/>the bridegrom, whych co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth we can not tell whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether at myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyght, or at the cockes crowynge, wherfore our mayſter Chriſt gaue vs warnyng that we ſhulde be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes wakyng, and loke vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly for he cometh cloſlye lyke a thefe, wythoute warnynge vs, at what houre he wyll come.</p>
            <p>Then as he findeth euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo wyll he iudge hym, and where the tree falleth whether it be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the South or North) there it lyeth: there is then no reſpite to be had, but ſtreyght waye due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of goddes iuſtice ſhal come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all fleſhe, happy is he therfore, whome hys maiſter at hys retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge fyndeth wakynge, for hym ſhall he put in auctoritie ouer all hys treaſure.</p>
            <p>And for ſo moche as then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tter ſhall hange al together in
<pb facs="tcp:1572:3"/>clearenes of conſcience, whyche at that tyme ſhall accuſe a man, or defende hym, acordynge as he hath kepte it cleane with vertues, or ſtayned wyth vices (for in the booke of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes concience are all theyr dedes layed vppe, to be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the audit day of our death) me thynk nothyng can be a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtaye to the concience of man, then to know how he ought to go owt of thys preſent lyfe, and what to cary wythhym to hys account, or leue behynd hym in the world.</p>
            <p>In conſyderation wherof I haue tranſlated in to my natyue ſpech out of Italie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter Barnardine Ochin teaching how a true chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to make hys laſt wyll: and for ſo moche as the diuell is at that inſtant of deth very bragging buſyly wyth man, and diuerſly troblith hym, and the
<pb facs="tcp:1572:4"/>iuſtice of god on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide fearith hym, I haue, to ſtaye &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſience on thes behalfes, tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in to engliſh two ſermons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructyng vs how to aunſwer the diuel whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he tempteth vs at what tym, &amp; by what meanes to quiet our myndes, as touching gods iuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tice, other two haue I alſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, whych enforme vs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true workes that god requireth of vs, and the way to go to heauen, and that our ſauiour chriſt Ieſus hath by hys moſt preciouſe death pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for vs paradiſe with out our deſeruynges.</p>
            <p>Wich fyue ſermons taken out of the firſt part of maiſter Barnar dine ſermons, as they be wrytten and publyſhed of good zeale to the wealth of many, ſo it is thy curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye (gentle reder) to accept them in good parte, &amp; pardon my groſſe
<pb facs="tcp:1572:4"/>tearmes as of a begynner, and beare wyth my tranſlation, as of a learner obteynynge thys of the good reader I ſhalbe redye and wyllynge hereafter when god ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth better knowlege (accordyng as my tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wyll extende) to turne mo godly ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſayd may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Barnardine into Engliſhe for the enformacion of all that deſyre to know the truth. For they truely conteyne moch to the defacyng of al papiſtrie, and hipocryſie, and to the aduancement of the glorye of god, and of the benefytes of Chriſt Ieſus. To whom wyth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſt be all honoure and glorye for euer and euer. So be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>GOD SAVE THE KYNG <hi>and graunt us the truthe of hys Worde.</hi>
               </hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1572:5"/>
            <head>HOW A CHRISTIAN OVGHT <hi>to make his laſt Wyll and Teſtamente.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>IT IS COMMONLY THE <hi>CVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of men in theyre teſtamentes, and</hi>
               </hi> laſt wylles to ſaye I leaue, I bequeath, I geue, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute onſe ſayinge I take or carye wyth me, wherin certes they be farre deceyued, bycauſe they take that, whyche they ought to leaue be hynde them, and go wythoute caryinge that whych is verye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hofefull and neceſſarye. Wherfore to the entent they ſhulde no more erre on that behalfe: I wolde we ſhulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder and weyghe how a true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld make hys wyll.</p>
            <p>Men that be either fooles, mad, phra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tike, neyther cä, nor yet know how to make a wyll, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue not wytte to deſcerne good
<pb facs="tcp:1572:5"/>from euyl, what is theyrs, or what is not, what to take, nor what to reſtore or bequeath, nor yet to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor in what maner. And yf hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelye they go about to make theyr teſtament, it ſhulde be but vayne and of no force god alloweth it not as a thyng made of a perſone wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Wherfore he that is wyllynge to make a teſtament effectuall (as expedient is to him that wylbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) behoueth to haue verye good ſpirituall iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, alyuely faith in Chriſte, and an vnderſtandynge and lyght aboue a naturall man, he muſt alſo be the ſonne, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heyre of god.</p>
            <p>And then he may ſaye: I ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of mynde, and redye of ſprite and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce, albeit as touchyng my fleſhe ſecke make my teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and bequeath fyrſt of all my being and ſubſtance to god: he gaue it to
<pb facs="tcp:1572:6"/>me and alſo preſerued it, and of hym I recogniſe to haue it, and for it I render hym thankes, I leaue to hym lykewyſe the gyftes, graces benefytes temporal, bodely and goſtlye, that I haue hadde, or ſhall here after receyue: for they be hys, and from him by grace I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege to haue receyued all, as Paule ſayeth, what haſt thou, that thou haſt not receyued at goddes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. yea for aſmoch as al the ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ders, myſreportes, perſecucions, ſyckenes, and myſfortunes, which I haue alreadye or ſhall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth ſuffer, and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death ſelfe, I confeſſe (by the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng that the Lorde hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me) that they haue bene and ſhalbe hys gyftes and graces, geuen and graunted of a great loue for my welthe and profyt: wherfore as hys diuine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes I Araunt to haue had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1572:6"/>of god, for them I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke hym, and as hys owne I leaue and reſtore them to hym.</p>
            <p>And for ſo moche as I can not but acknowledge that I haue goue alwayes backewarde from hym ſo often as I wolde rule my ſelfe by my blynde iudgemente, folyſhe wyſdome, and deueliſhe ſprite nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dyd ſo moch as go one ſteppe forth towarde God, but when I was moued, diyuen, and thruſte forwarde of his holy ſprite. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I commytte to the hygheſte god my moſt deare father, and to hys gouernance, al the worlde and ſpecially my ſelf: in him (as I may) I wyll helpe my ſelfe wyth myne owne witte, and fredome, namely by makynge it obedient to hym.</p>
            <p>Moreouer if euer I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or ſhall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth vtter any word, if I haue done or ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:1572:7"/>do any worke, that is to hym ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte if I haue had or after thys tyme ſhall haue thought deſier or wyll, that good is, I geue it to god, and at hys handes I profeſſe that I haue had al my goodnes, ſo that if it were gods wyll, to take from me all that he hathe geuen me, there ſhulde in me remayne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng but onely ſynnes: thoſe are myne owne, and all other thyngs be hys.</p>
            <p>Thus be my ſynnes if I ſhulde go before gods preſence. I were but damned, if I were minded to make ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I coulde not, no nor yet any ſaynte that euer was, ther is none whoſe loue is ſo great to take my ſynnes vppon hym and ſat yſfye for them, and appeaſe goddes angre ſaue Chryſt a lone, wherfore to hym I bequeth my ſynnes, I leue to hym my pryde,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:7"/>vnkyndnes, vnbeleue, miſtruſte, arrogancy, enuy, wrath, ambition and all my vn numerable wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: I geue to him my euil though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, affections, &amp; deſiers: to be ſhort I make one fagott and boundell of all my offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces preſent, paſt, and to com, and geue them to Chriſte hauynge ſure faythe, and ſtedfaſt hope, that he wyll accepte them for hys owne, &amp; hath euen alredy taken them, and for them hath ſatiſfied on the croſſe, hys father layed them on hys necke,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 53.</note> and he did not ones agayne ſay it, but of great loue allowed them for hys, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume and burne them in the flame of hys diuine loue, he bore them on hys Innocent ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 3.</note> (as peter wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teh) &amp; ſo was offred a ſacrifice for vs. Now ſeyng I haue lefte almy ſynns to Chriſt, and geuen to god
<pb facs="tcp:1572:8"/>my ſubſtance, and beyng, wyth all other gyftes &amp; graces, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on me. I remayne naked wythout eyther good or euyl, and truelye to ſaye, I am rather no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, In that I haue reſtored to god my beynge that I had by cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and byrth.</p>
            <p>But for bycauſe it is impoſſible that he ſhuld ſaue me wythout be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, and ſo it is that he wyll ſaue me, therfore fyrſt I carye with me Chriſt hym ſelfe, whych is my lyfe. God hath ſo loued me,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.</note> that he hath geuen hym ſelfe to me. For ſo hath god loued the world, that for theyr ſynnes he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs hys onely begotten ſonne. I carye alſo with me his ſprite, that was of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall father geuen me of hys moſt royal liberalytie, as wel declareth Paule,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> where he ſayeth, god hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſprite of hys ſonne into our
<pb facs="tcp:1572:8"/>hertes wherby we crye and call father, father.</p>
            <p>And in that he hath geuen me hym, he hath reſtored me to my ſelfe and former beinge, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a new ſubſtance and nature ſpirituall, ſo that for the poſſibilite of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I haue a beinge: but yet lacke I treaſure to diſcharge my great dettes, &amp; to apere rych in goddes ſight, in conſyde racion whereof I bere wyth me chriſtes watchyng, abſtinences, traueyls, prayeres, perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſcla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, I take with me his teares, hys ſwet, his, blood, and all that euer he did or ſuffered in thre and thyrtty yeres is myne every deal, and wyth lyuely fayth I embrace it as for myne owne. I carye byſyde this wyth me hys patience, mekenes, loue, and all other his diuine vertues, hys gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and graces, hys treſurs, and
<pb facs="tcp:1572:9"/>and all that he hath mereted and deſeruid, hys lyfe, paſſyon, death, reſurrection &amp; aſſenſion be myne, ye all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euer he hath done or ſhall from henceforth do is myne. and what nedeth more to ſaye, if god haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs hys own ſonne, how hath not he wyth hym geuen vs all thynges, wherfore wyth faith I embrace my ſweete Ieſus for myne owne, he is my ryghtwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Corin.</hi> 1.</note> wiſdome, raunſom, &amp; holynes he is my ſtrength, he is my ſprite, my lyght, lyfe, hope, &amp; all my good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt hymſelfe in hys laſt wyll bequethed me all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had of the father. wherfore he ſayeth, I entertayn you at my table as my father hath vſed me,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as my father hath made me hys heyre ſo now I ordeyne you, I wyll that as you be my bretherne ſo you ſhalbe my folowers: And in another place he
<pb facs="tcp:1572:9"/>ſayeth I haue loued you, as my fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath loued me ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>through chriſt ſo rych of treaſures, vertuſe, &amp; graces, I ſhalbe hable not onely toſatilfy for my deites, but alſo to purchaſe infinite para diſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer they ſhalbe ſould.</p>
            <p>Who ſhalbe now either to acuſe or condemne me, after that chriſt hath thus clothed me wyth hys innoſency, ryghtwyſnes, holynes, loue, with al hys vertuſe, graces, treaſures, merites, and with hys ownſelf, I may wyth no leſſe bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denes and ſuretie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt, ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are before god, I am hys ſonne, as he is, and heyre of heauen, ſemblably I am innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as chriſte is now that he hath ſatyſtied for me, and payed my raunſom, and rewarded me wyth hys innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Chriſte ſayed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.</note> I hallow my ſelf that they alſo may be holye, euen
<pb facs="tcp:1572:10"/>he is our holynes, and we be hys me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers. wherfore it is as poſſible for god not to loue me, as it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that he ſhuld not loue chriſte by reaſon wherof Paule ſayeth who ſhall deuid me from the loue of god that is in Chriſte Ieſu.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 8.</note> it muſte nedes be that he be ſalued, whych wyth lyuing fayth embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Chriſte for hys owne. And conſyderyng that the treaſures, and merites of Chriſt are infinite, and able to enryche a thowſand worldes, I entende not to carye with me any other merites, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall riches, ſaue thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte hath prouyded for me, for they be not onely ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for me, but alſo ouer abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and vnmeſurable.</p>
            <p>Then ſhuld I do no ſmal iniuri to Chriſt, if I ſhuld ſearch to ſtore my ſelfe by any other meane or ſhyfte, although I myght do it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:1572:10"/>ſo eaſely, nay rather w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule wyll I rekenne all other thynges as myre and dyrt ſo that I haue Chriſte,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.</note> wyth whom alone I wyll appeare before god, and of and by hym wyl I glory and make boaſt, yea god forbydde,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 6.</note> that I ſhuld ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke my auaunte of any thyng, ſaue of the croſſe of our lord Ieſu Chriſt of whome onely hangeth all oure health. And all beit al the ſayntes be riche by meane of Chriſt, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, yf they hadde meanes of theyr owne moſt ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuoſe, &amp; wolde geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me, yet would I none, my Chriſte is inough for me, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him had I rather ſuffer, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; ioye without him. It would be a thing pleaſaunt to me, yf eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhulde make prayer to god for me, not bycauſe I myght pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, or haue any other treaſures the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe that I haue of Chriſt, but
<pb facs="tcp:1572:11"/>that I might by liuely faith euery daye acknowlege poſſeſſe and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thoſe that I haue receyued of Chriſte, and count the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for myne and ſo enforme my ſelfe, I myſelf were it not by Chriſte, ſhulde not know what to aſke, for in him is al and with out hym all other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be but mere vanitie, only this peticyon I make to hym, that he voucheſafe euery daye to geue me light and vnderſtandynge, that I may haue wytte to accounte and take his treaſures for nyne owne. Wherfore yf any man wyll praye for me let hym not tarye tyll I be deade, for then I can no more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in light and grace. Let him praye nowe, that I may grow in faith and more and more inſtructe my ſelfe of Chriſtes ryches. I am well aſſured that in purgatorye I ſhalnot come, both bicauſe ther is
<pb facs="tcp:1572:11"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no other purgatory but chriſt in whom at the full be purged and puniſhed al the ſynnes of the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and alſo bycauſe in caſe there were one) yet Chryſte not by my merytes, but by hys mere good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dothe ſatiſfie for al my ſynnes treſpaſſes, &amp; paynes, &amp; for as moch as hope neuer made any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded any perſone,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 3</note> that had it in hys harte (as Pauſe wrote) therfore am I ſure and ſec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker that he wyll ſaue me without other purgacion. We can not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe our ſelfes to moch of goddes goodnes, no we neuer ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vehete vs ſo moche, but he wyll recompence moch more. I wyl not ſuffer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that after my lyfe any good be done for me. Truth it is that yf I haue any goodes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt I leaue to the poore flocke of Chriſt, not bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhuld praye for me, that
<pb facs="tcp:1572:12"/>am already ſaued, but for the vſe of other that lyue, &amp; ſhalbe borne, as Chriſt dyd,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on.</hi> 17.</note> and alſo bycauſe the rather they may lyue godlye, and knowe that they ſhal neuer lacke that be hys, and putte theyr truſt in hym. To whome be alwayes, honour and glory through Ieſu Chriſte our Lorde Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>HOW WE SHVLD ANSWER <hi>the deuel VVhen he tempteth us and namely in the ende of our lyfe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE DEVELL (AS PETER <hi>uuriteth</hi>) <hi>ſeketh aluuay to deuour us</hi>
               </hi> but chefely he is buſy at the houre of deth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Petri.</hi> 5.</note> by reaſon then it ſtande the hym in hande ſo to do for hys owne behooue, and our greater endomage and harme.
<pb facs="tcp:1572:12"/>Then vſeth he all myght, power, ſleyght, deceyte, &amp; malice: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thynke good that we ſhulde ſearch how to make hym anſwer and by the aſſiſtence and ayde of godes grace to wythſtande hym, and gett the vpper hande of hym,</p>
            <p>He is conſtraygned ſpecially when we aproch nere to our deth, to throw vs in to the aſiſſe and pyt of deſperacion, or els to ſet vs vp in pryde and preſumpcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. if he ſhal perceue that thou either put truſt in thy ſelfe, or confidence in thyne own workes, he wyl not go inha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſpayre &amp; miſtruſt gods mercy, but rather ſtabliſhe the in that erronyouſe opinion of pryde of thy dedes on the other ſyde if he fele that thou haſt all thy hope in god: then wyll he ſhew the on the one partie the multitude and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of thy ſynnes, and on the
<pb facs="tcp:1572:13"/>other partie goddes wrathe and ſeuere iuſtice, he wyl tell the how thou art in a maze and perplexitie not able to be ſhaken of, or wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den owt of, and by makyng the to feel thyne offences, other wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer thou deddeſt in thy health wyll go a boute to take owte of thy harte the paſſion of chriſte, and all the great goodnes, mercy, and loue of god, &amp; finally to proue the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he wyl bryng for hys purpoſe-euen the holy ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>But I wyll that al hys te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ſerue the to the honour of god and ſaluacion of thy ſoule as they do ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> turne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elected,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 3.</note> to whom all thynges woorke to gether for theyr wealth, fyrſte of all I warne the, that thou mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn not thy ſelfe for good, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt and graunt all the euill that he ſhall reherſe of the and thynke,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:13"/>that he hathe not ſayed ſo moche,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn. ii.</hi>
               </note> but that it is moch more: &amp; thanke god that now at laſte he hathe be ſo fauorable, to make the conſider thy ſinnes, wherin he vſeth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel for an inſtrument, to the ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that by the knowyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thow ſhuldeſt take occaſion to humble thy ſelfe, and to call Chriſt to thy remembrance, whych to ſcoure and clenſe them hath not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putid them for hys own, but alſo dyed for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the croſſe grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thou hardely that thou art a grete rybald and noghtye wythout ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſyng thy ſelf in any wyſe, &amp; that thy ſynnes are in numerable. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that thou cold neuer ſatiſfie for one alone, and that thou were the moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned ſinner of the world yf Chriſte had not delyuered ſhe, and ſtyl pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte thy ſelfe with thoſe matters, whych may forther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:1572:14"/>com in to deſperacion of thy ſelfe:</p>
            <p>But if the diuel wayt to bring the to deſpeyr of Chriſt, thou may in no wyſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ther to, but ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtlye put thy truſt in hym. and my mynd is that thou ſay to hym thus. if it were good for me to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> neuer woldeſt haue perſwaded me therto but rather haue drawne me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, wherfore in that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> woldeſt put me in mynde to miſtruſte Chriſt, thou makeſte me ſtronger in my hope and truſt.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt ſaye to hym, that when he cauſed iniuſtly Chriſte to dye, whych was an Innocent, he loſt al his interprieſt &amp; iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that euer he had or poſſible might haue ouer man. and if he procede forthe to induce the to diſpayer, by ſettynge before the thy greate ſynnes, I wyll the to ſay to hym. go to Chryſte, whyche (as Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:1572:14"/>wryteth) is myne attourney and Aducoate,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> he can make the an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for me, reaſon there wyth hym, yf thou haue any clayme or tytle in me, as thou ſayeſt, doeſt thou not know that he hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſynnes for hys owne, and hath for them made ſatiſtactyou moſte plentuouſly, therfore haſt thou no ryght in me at all.</p>
            <p>If he chaunce to ſay hys death is not inough to ſaue the, anſwere him, yf Adam by taſting one apple wyth one onely ſynne was hable to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne me: how is it that ſo many holy workes of Chriſt, which taſted for my ſake of great loue the moſt bytter deathe, be not ſuffycient to ſaue me.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> If the diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had power to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne me, moch more the obedyence of Chriſte is ſtronge inough to ſaue me, yea the gyfte of Chriſt is aboue and exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:1572:15"/>the ſynne of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Chriſt hath more auayled and holpen vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adam annoied and harmed vs by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyght of Chriſt is of more force and effecte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the darkenes of our fyrſt parente, the goodnes of Chriſtes ſurmounteth and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the malyce of man, &amp; hys ver tue preuaileth about our fraylty: one teare of Chriſt hath bene more pleaſaunt to god, then all the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the worlde be diſpleaſaunt Chriſte hath be able to do more to appeace hym, then we to prouoke him to anger, Chriſtes liuyng was more formall and ordinarye, then oures was out of ordre and frame Chriſte hath done more to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of god, then we haue done to hys diſhonour. Wherfore I maye well ſay, Chriſt that is my wiſdom, right wiſnes,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor,</hi> 1.</note> holynes, &amp; redemcion is ſufficient inought to ſaue me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1572:15"/>And if haplye he ſhulde ſay, it is not ſufficient for thy ſaluacion to beleue in Chriſte, the behoueth to kepe hys commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, thou muſt loue god wyth all thy harte, and thy neyghboure as thy ſelfe, and deſier nor couet anye thynge worldlye, whych thyngs becauſe thou doeſt not, ergo, thou art da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if fayth onlye were inough I alſo &amp; all the diuels ſhuld beſaued, becauſe (as yt is wrytten) euen the deuels beleue &amp; feare.
<note place="margin">lames. ii.</note> They beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god made &amp; created heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt came, dyed, roſe, aſcended in to heuen, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heſent the holy ghoſt, &amp; that he ſhal come to iudge the quicke &amp; dead, and yet are not we therfore ſaued, &amp; that bicauſe we obſerue not his diuine preceptes. wherfore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> alſo art but loſt, he wyll thus labour to bryng the vnder the law, to thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou
<pb facs="tcp:1572:16"/>be iuſtified not by chriſt, but by per fourmynge and fulfyllynge of the lawe, to the ende that thou ſhulde deſpayre.</p>
            <p>But I wyl that thou make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſay, yf thou dyddeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue as by goddes grace I beleue: that is, that god for thy wealthe hath created the worlde, and ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably preſerueth it, in ſuch ſorte that thou couldeſt fele in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the loue of god, &amp; lykewyſe wolde beleue firmely, that Chriſte came and dyed for thy ſynnes, for to ſaue the, and for thy ſake &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt, and in lyke maner of the other articles, thou alſo ſhulde be ſaued, and then, when thou haddeſt a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely feling of the goodnes and loue of god thou woldeſt loue hym, and thy neyghbour likewyſe, &amp; beynge rauiſhed into god woldeſt beginne to ſet litle ſtore by the worlde as al
<pb facs="tcp:1572:16"/>good Chriſten men and women do If it fortune that he ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut. xx</hi> 7</note> he is cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that kepeth not and obſerueth the law, wherfore thou art one of myne, ſaye to him agayne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 3</note> for that cauſe chriſt dyed on the croſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 7</note> for to delyuer me from all curſes, and in ſomoche as I am all ready of chriſt I am dead to the law.</p>
            <p>Agayn yf he reply eſaying, wher be thy workes, wherby thou truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to be ſaued, anſwere, I truſt not to be ſaued by my workes, for they be ſoch that yf I ſhulde haue regarde or reſpecte to them, I feare me to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, yea I were ſurely aſcerteyned of my damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 8.</note> I hope onelye to be ſaued by Chriſt, and hys workes, whyche be myne owne, and ſo moche rather myne, then they I dyd my ſelfe, as that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprite of chriſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me is more entyer to me then myne own
<pb facs="tcp:1572:17"/>lyfe or any other thyng.</p>
            <p>Further yf he ſhuld endeuoure to proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to be none of the electe, by reaſon of the innumerable, and outragiouſe ſynnes that thou haſt committed, for proſperites, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſites thou haſt had, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great euils wherin thou arte founde at thy deathe, or for the temtacions thou haſt ſuſteyned, ſayinge, that god preſerueth his elected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like euels. make hym anſwer and ſay:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 3.</note> rather doth god practiſe them in diuerſe ſoche maners, albeit of euery thynge they be certifyed to the honor of god, thou ſhalt more ouer ſay to hym thus. I geue more credite and truſt to chriſt, whiche when he was deade for me on the croſſe, tould me I was ſaued, then to the, that art always alyer and father of erroures. I wyll thou tel hym, how thou geueſt more fayth
<pb facs="tcp:1572:17"/>to Chriſt alone, then to al the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and autorities of the worlde: thou may byſyde thys ſay to hym, the ſprite of god bearyth wytneſſe to my ſprite,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 8.</note> that I am the ſonne of god, and to hym muſt I rather truſt then to the. when he ſhal ſay, if thou were the ſonne of god he woulde not leaue the in ſouch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as thou art in, but wold giue the ſome releaſe and eaſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Anſwer hym, In caſe it were as thou ſayeſt Chriſt ſhulde not haue bene the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god, ſithen on the croſſe he had no comfort, nor ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual taſt or feling, ſo that he ſaied my god,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marci.</hi> 15.</note> my god why haſte thou forſaken me: it ſufficith to me that he ſhe wyth me ſo moche fauouer, for I am contented wyth all that pleaſethe hym, as Chryſte alſo was, yea in hys ſufferynge, he
<pb facs="tcp:1572:18"/>felte excedynglye the infinite loue of the father.</p>
            <p>Beſyde theſe of he ſay:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he. ii.</note> thou art the ſonne of Adam, ergo thou art acurſed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn.</hi> 1.</note> Anſwere thou thus: I am bleſſed agayne by beyng borne of god, and by meane of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſede Chriſt as god longe agone promyſed Adam when he ſayed.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ene. xii.</note> In thy ſede al nacions ſhalbe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, thou ſhalt tell hym: how thou art deſpoiled and bereſt of the olde Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oma.</hi> 13</note> and clothed with Ieſu Chriſt as Paule teacheth and aduerty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the.</p>
            <p>What tyme as he ſhal declare to the that chriſt is wroth, angry and ſharpe: make hym anſwere howe Chriſt is not ſoch one, for he is the healthe and hope of ſynners, and whyleſt we be in thys lyfe preſent he is vttered to vs pytiful, ſweete, and our Ieſus, that is, our ſauiour
<pb facs="tcp:1572:18"/>and albeit heſeme to ſpeke ſharpe, and cruel wordes to the woman of Cananye,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet in herte he gaue her confydence and boldneſſe, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed hym ſelf to her full of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue. In dede at the daye of iudgement to the damned ſhall he be ſhewed angry, and wrathful but in the meane tyme tyll that day while we be here in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life, he is ſhewed pitiouſe to al, and principally to the great ſynners.</p>
            <p>And yf it ſo were that he wolde ſaye thou art not trulye confeſſed, nor haſte reherſed all thy ſynnes, and the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances of the ſame, ne haſt examyned ſuffyciently thy conſcyence, nor yet haſt not that pure perfecte great, and vnfayned ſorow for thy ſynnes that thou of dutye ſhuldeſt haue, thou haſt not ſatyſfyed for thoſe ſo great an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable dettes, that thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:1572:19"/>towarde god, make hym thys an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſaye: thou art a ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and not a iudge: or to ſaye more truelye,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 3.</note> thou art all ready iudged and condemned, ſeyng thou bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt not in Chriſt, and woldeſt thou indge mettrouble thy ſelfe no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in prouing that I haue failed in al, for ſure I am, and fully I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue to be ſaued, not by my workes by reaſon they be vnperfecte, nor yet by the worthynes of my fayth, for in that alſo I am not perfecte, bycauſe I beleue not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo great a faith as I oughte, but I beleue I ſhalbe ſaued by Chriſte, and not by my workes.</p>
            <p>He wyl ſay: thou art not worthy to be ſaued, ſaye thou to hym for a ful anſwer: the vnworthy be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ued ſo often as they acknowledge theyr owne vnworthynes, go hartelye for helpe to Chriſt, by whoſe meane
<pb facs="tcp:1572:19"/>they be come worthy.</p>
            <p>Where as he ſhall laye to thy charge that thou arte one of the worſt of the worlde: ſay to hym on thys wyſe our infyrmyties be but ſmal in compariſon of the infinite merites of Chriſte, and of the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible mercy of god: and the more great that my ſynnes be and without number, ſo moch greater ſhalbe hys glory in deliuering me, and I wyth ſo moche the greater truſt pray as that yf he wyll heare me, it ſhalbe more to hys honoure and glory. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder and call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that my ſwete and louyng brother Ieſus Chriſte the ſonne of god, which for my ſake dyed on the croſſe, &amp; wolde agayne innumerable times for me, yf nede were, &amp; that I am hys owne for ſo many cauſes, &amp; that he may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of me after his owne mynde.
<pb facs="tcp:1572:20"/>For ſomoch as his father hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hym full power in heuen and earth: when I conſyder thys, I ſaye, I canin no wyſe dout of my ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>If he efte ſoones reaſon thus: thou haſt done no penance for thy ſynnes: anſwere on thys maner: that can I neuer do, yf I ſhoulde alwaye ſtande in the fyre, Chriſte hath done that for me on the croſſe more ouer, Chriſte is myne, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hathe geuen hym to me wyth all hys merites, all the good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that euer he dyd are myne, wherfore I maye wyth hys deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ryches, and treaſures ſatyſfye for all.</p>
            <p>After this maner I wolde thou ſhulde anſwere hym, when ſoeuer he ſetteth afore the thy ſinnes, and infynite dettes, that thou oughteſt to god for the benefites, thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:1572:20"/>receyued wyth dyuerſe and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry vyces whyl he tempte the, but ſpecyally wyth deſperacion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth he tempteth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaintes he wyll put the in mynde and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſte that Chriſte hath forſaken the: but make anſwer that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forſoke perſone that truſted in hym, but bycauſe he wold forſake none of vs, he was mynded to be forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelfe on the croſſe, and yf he ſhoulde at any tyme forſake and refuſe vs (the which is a thing impoſſyble) it ſhoulde be for more glorye of god, and we oughte not onely to be contented, but alſo to take it for a ſyngular pryuylege and prerogatiue. It behoueth vs to ſtande ſtronge in the fayth, and thynke that afore god the paſſyon of Chriſt can do more to cauſe him to loue vs, then oure ſynnes can procure hys hate towarde vs, we
<pb facs="tcp:1572:21"/>hadde nede to be wel armed wyth ſpryte, ſayth, and grace, for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge ſufficeth not to know how to aunſwer, and wyte thou well that Chriſt was tempted, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally at the ende, wherfore he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn.</hi> 15.</note> the prynce of thys worlde is comene, but he hathe gotten no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge of me.</p>
            <p>And yf he can not wy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h theſe armour hurte the, he wyll turne ouer the leafe, and ſay thus, and all bycauſe to deceaue the. go to thou haſte alredy vanquiſhed me, I was myneded to brynge the in to deſperacyon, but I colde not. thou arte ſaued: and by and by wyll the angels com to fett the.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ii. Corin.</hi> 15.</note> he wyll apere to the like an angell of lyght, and ſaye to the as he did to ſaynte hilarion. haſte thou ſerued god ſo long, haſt thou done ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good dedes ſo greate penance,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:21"/>geuen ſo many good enſamples, ſaued ſo many ſoules: and all beit thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſynns, yet art thou confeſſed of them, thou haſt done pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thou haſt taken par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dones, thou haſte gone for indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, thou kepeſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and beſyde theſe done many volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary workes that thou waſt not bounden to do, wherfore why ſhuldeſt thou feare. thou ſhalt be ſafe and ſure, if thou be not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then ſhall none be ſaued. yea thy good woorkes be ouer pluſe, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The deuell is a lyar. Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> which thou may ſell or geue to other, whych if thou do not the Church of Rome ſhalbe thy heyre, and thou ſhalt enryche theyr treaſory of indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. what fereſt thou therfore: haſt thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply gone another path or way. al beit thou haue admitted ſines, yet ſeeſte thou not how thou art well
<pb facs="tcp:1572:22"/>diſpoſed at the laſte, onelye ſtande ſtoutlye in the truſte of theſe thy great and manye good woorkes, ſuffer thys ſicknes, and death for the remiſſion of thy ſynnes, &amp; thou ſhalt be more then ſaued, onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thy ſelfe. of thy good woorkes. Then it is expedient for the to ſaye thus. Thou wouldeſte that I ſhuld truſt in my woorkes, and I haue no fere of being dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, were it not for my woorkes, I geue thankes to my lord Chriſte Ieſus, whych hath geuen me the grace to counte my woorkes for a thing of nought, and for ſuch, that euery one of them I deſerue to be punyſhed, thou magnyfy eſte my woorkes, to draw me backe from the confydence of Chriſte, but by gods grace, thou ſhalt not be able to do it. I fynde that I am vpon a litle bourd in the ſea toſſed wyth
<pb facs="tcp:1572:22"/>mighty wyndes, and haue embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and beclepped a ſtrong pyller or rocke, and thou cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celeſt me to leaue it, and to ſticke to the roten thynges whych if I ſhulde do, the wyndes wolde cary bothe me and them in to the ſea. rather I wyll peryſhe wyth Chriſte whyche is a thing impoſſible I then lyue with owte hym, no I cane not put my truſt holy in Chriſt oneles firſte al to gether I diſpayer of my ſelfe and myne owne woorkes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary that we diſpoil our ſelfes of all truſt in our owne woorkes, and by fayth and hope, clothe vs and arme vs with Chriſt and in hym put oure hope, and al though we haue not that greate fayth, yet in no wyſe ought we to deſpayre, bycauſe if at the firſte he do not, yet at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghthe he geueth it to hys elected at theyr deathe,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:23"/>as the prophete Abacucke tolde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehande, when he ſayed, Lorde when they ſhalbe nere to the deth at the latter ende, betwene thys waye and the other, thou wylte make knowen to them Chriſte and his great benefytes, and wylte open to them the boſome of thy graces by Ieſu Chriſte oure Lorde. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <head>HOW ANSWER IS TO <hi>be made at the iudgement ſeate of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>AFELON OR GVYLTYPAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>that can not flye, but of neceſſytie</hi>
               </hi> muſt apeare at the ſeſſions aſſyſe, or lawedaye afore the barre, picketh out and choſeth hym for hys ayed and ſuccoure,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:23"/>attourneys, protectours, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeylours, and gothe deuiſyng how he maye be defended, namely in a matier touchyng elyfe and death: whyche thynge it ſtandeth vs in hande more to do. In ſo moch as, that we beyng full of ſinnes, muſt apeare afore the hygh iudgement ſeate of goddes iuſtyce, and when iudgement by defynitiue ſentence is geuen agaynſte vs, we ſhall loſe paradiſe, ſoule, grace, god, and all goodnes wythout recouerye, and be throwen in to the depe pytte of hell, there to remayne and abyde in fyre euerlaſtingly. Wherfore me ſemeth it were expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to imagin what waye to take, what anſwer to make wyth what reaſons to arme vs, that we maye haue the mattyer to paſſe on oure ſyde.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt of all an vndouted matter
<pb facs="tcp:1572:24"/>is it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 5.</note> that we all haue ſynned in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, and beſyde the origynal ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne haue innumerable actuall, ne can be ſaued, onles fyrſt we be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that muſt nedes be whileſt we be in this lyfe for after warde is, no more redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion at all.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luce</hi> 16.</note> To the gloton was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed one droppe of water.</p>
            <p>Wherfore neceſſary it is to know that there be two iudgement ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of god: the one is of ryghtwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenes, the other of mercy, grace, pytie, goodnes, loue ſwetnes, and lyberalitie:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebre.</hi> 4.</note> as Paule ſpeakyng of thys laſt fayth. let vs go boldlye to the trone, and bench of gods grace at the firſt bench ſitteth god, and Chryſte kepeth reſydence at the ſecond. Now as for the ſinners, if they wylve ſaued they muſt go all to the benche of mercy to aſke and call for pitie, and not iuſtice, for
<pb facs="tcp:1572:24"/>fauoure and ſtrayght reconynge, bycauſe we haue all bene vniuſte, and with alour ryght wyſnes, and good workes be not hable to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande goddes rightwiſenes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dauid ſayed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> Lord none can be iuſtyfyed in thy ſyghte, yf there thou wyltſee a reconynge, and in another place,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. cxxix.</note> Lord yf thou wylt puniſhe our iniquities, who ſhalbe hable to abyde: and Iob ſayeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.</note> I know that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not be iuſtified yf he ſtande face to face afore god. And in another place,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.</note> what thyng is man that he ſhoulde be cleane: the heauens be not cleane in hys ſyght.
<note place="margin">Ieremye. ii.</note> And Ieremye wryteth thus If thou waſhe the wyth nytrus thou ſhalt neuertheleſſe be ſtained And Eſaye ſayeth: our ryght wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenes be lyke the clothes of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<note place="margin">Prouer. xx.</note> and Salomon wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the ſame, ſayeng who is he
<pb facs="tcp:1572:25"/>that can ſaye my harte is cleane, I am pure &amp; innocent from ſinne, wherefore ſayeth god by Ierymy, why wyl you ſtriue with me in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: As though he ſhuld ſay you are fooles, if you thynk your ſelfe hable to wythſtande the iuſtice of god, ſeing youre ryght wyſnes ys vncleane, and that ſomoch vncle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as that not onely the workes, but alſo the very i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ward thoughts, affections, and deſires ſhalbe exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and tryed. therfore ſayeth god: I wyl ſearch. trye and proue. Ieruſalem.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sopho.</hi> 1</note> wyth lanternes. it is moſte profitable therefore to go to the bench of mercy. And ſay wyth Dauid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 15.</note> Lord I ſhalcom afore the, not with the multitude of my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, but of thy mercy, and in caſe thou be ſommoned and called to the trone of iuſtice, appeale to the other bench of mercy, for as from
<pb facs="tcp:1572:25"/>the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a lord ſubiecte to the Emperour a man may appeale to Ceſars iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeate: ſo may a man appeale from the benche of iuſtice to the trone of mercy as to the hygher court. In aſmoche as Iames writeth mercy ercelleth iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice: it is ſene that Ezechyas,
<note place="margin">Iames. ii.</note> after ſentence was gyuen vpon hym at the benche of iuſtyce,
<note place="margin">iiii. Regu.</note> bycauſe he appealed to the other Throne of mercy had graunted to hym, that he ſhuld lyue fyftene yeres longer. And Dauid by appealyng to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy cauſed the ſentence to be reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<note place="margin">ii. Regu. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which was gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he ſhuld dye. And what tyme that ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</note> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goſpel ſpeaketh, ſayed, haue pacience with me &amp; gyue me reſpite: he appealed to mercy and was herde. In like maner is it and hath be of al ſinners that be ſaued</p>
            <p>Now muſte we do in the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:1572:26"/>wyſe, I meane when we be cyted to the court of iuſtice to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der and yelde an accompte, then muſt we appeale to mercy, and ſaye: we be dead through Chriſt to the law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 7.</note> and therfore to iuſtice alſo, which iudge after the lawe are we deade, then hath iuſtice no iurildictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon vs at al, no though it were the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſynner of the world: ſaye thou to god, I am Chriſtes, thou gaueſt me to hym, as Chriſte ſayeth: they were thyne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.</note> &amp; thou haſt gyuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me. Moreouer Chriſt hath rede medme, therfor am I his for many cauſes, I wyl therfore ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to hys iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: thou haſt giuen him all power in heauen &amp; in earth as he himſelfe ſayeth:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> to me is gyuen all power in he auen &amp; in earth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he may do with me the thyng that lyketh him, and as to him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth good, he is my iudge as Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:1572:26"/>hymſelfe ſayeth:
<note place="margin">Iohn. xii.</note> the father hath giuen aliudgement to the ſonne, it is therfore his dutye to iudge me. But as in another place he ſayeth he came not to iudge but to ſaue the worlde, ſay therfore to Chriſt: do thyne offyce, ſaue me, for thou cameſt, and thy father dyd ſende the for that ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I feele all redy thy voyce, &amp; in my harte thou ſaieſt to me, that bycauſe I truſt in the, thou wylt ſaue me, alredye by thy grace haue I put in the my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence &amp; hope, and he,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exodi.</hi> 19.</note> that beleueth in the can not be damned, ſaue me therfore accordyng as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by a couenaunt made. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience accuſed the, and all the deuels beſyde layed to thy charge, ye a though iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>: yer ſo long as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life, it is alway lauful to appeale to the mercy of god.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1572:27"/>And yf it were ſo, that by force thou ſhuld be drawen to the court of iuſtice, crye out wyth Iſay, and ſaye to Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ty.</hi> 38.</note> o Lorde I ſuffer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, make anſwere for me, helpe me, forſake me not, I choſe and wyl haue the for my attorney and ſpeche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: not bycauſe thou ſhuld defende my iuſte accomptes, and true reckeninges, for I haue none ſoch, but to thentent thou ſhulde take my ſynnes for thyne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde me with thyne innocencye, holynes, &amp; right witnes. Thou haſt already ſatiſfyed for me on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe and appoynted me by adopcion to be the ſonne of god, wherfore I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be damned, no not one ſhalbe founde that dare accuſe me,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioma.</hi> 8.</note> being one of goddes elected.</p>
            <p>More ouer yf thou be myneded and wyllyng to appeare wythout daunger at the benche of goddes
<pb facs="tcp:1572:27"/>ryght wyſnes dyſpoyle fyrſte thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of the olde Adam, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell the wyth Chriſt (as Paule ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs,) and thou ſhalbe ſafe.
<note place="margin">Colloſen</note> For in ſomoch as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt embraced him for thyne owne, thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned all though thou haddeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted al the ſinnes of the worlde. As a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great with childe can not be puniſhed, no more can thou,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoca.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yf thou haue Chriſt in thy hart,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> or rather (as Chriſte ſayeth) he that beleueth in the ſonne is not iudged he is ſo aſſured of hys ſaluacyon, that there nedeth no examinacion to be had of hym, he is one of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes membres, and hath his ſprite, wherfore he can no more be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, bicauſe he is knytte to hym by lyuely fayth.</p>
            <p>If it be ſo that god wolde make there with the a rekenyng, ſaye to hym how thou haſt made it wyth
<pb facs="tcp:1572:28"/>Chriſt, for as he put on Chriſte all our iniquities and ſinnes (as I ſay ſayeth) &amp; with great loue accepted them for his owne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ye.</hi> 53.</note> and bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de him ſelf to make ſatiſfaction for them. Wherfore thou ſhalt ſay, Lorde yf thou haſt any reconing or matter againſt me, make it with Chriſt he knoweth wel how to anſwer &amp; can declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hath ſatiſfyed for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>In caſe be that any muſt be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the ſynnes I haue done, it is Chriſt, that muſt be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, and not I good Lorde, for albeit I am he that committed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuer the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Chriſt bounde hym ſelfe to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffie for them, and that by conſent and good wyl of his father, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoeuer be leueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uely in Chriſt is al together ſafe and ſure</p>
            <p>Beſyde this yf god wolde nedes make the audite &amp; accompte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, and wolde ſay: I am not content
<pb facs="tcp:1572:28"/>with Chriſtes ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you, I wyl that your ſelfes make recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded (which is a thing impoſſible) alredy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, &amp; hath ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepted that denine ſacrifice of the vndefiled la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be Chriſt Ieſus, which dyed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe to be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his father (as Paul hath write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) alredy is the right wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of god ſatiſfyed by chriſt more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficient,
<note place="margin">Philip. ii.</note> we be airedy reconſiled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god, and made his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly his heires he hath alredy geuen vs paradiſe, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath onſe giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a gifte it neuer repenteth hym:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 11</note> wherfore the gyft can not be called agayne bireaſon god is not chan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable I neuertheleſſe althoughe (as I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed) he ſhuld ſay: I wyll that thou thy ſelfe ſatiſfye. Anſwere hym on thys wyſe: Lorde yf I were as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re beloued to the, as is Chriſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:1572:29"/>had doone and ſuffered louynglye for thy honour. all that Chriſt did and ſuffered, in thys caſe woldeſſe thou not holde thy ſelfe ſufficiently ſatiſfied for me: in caſe he grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted therto. thou ſhuld make hym this anſwer. then is it alredy done. for in that Chriſt ſuffered I any ſelfe ſuffered, by reaſone I am chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into Chriſt. ye a the true Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianes, that haue Chriſte in theyr hartes (as Paule ſayith let Chriſt dwel in our harts) may pittiouſly lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; complayne to of god,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; ſay to hym: thou haſt puniſhed vs more bitterlye then we haue deſerued, conſideryng that we offended and not Chriſte, reaſone woulde thou ſhuld haue puniſhed vs, our wyll, and oure lyfe and ſoule, and not that innocent and vndefiled lambe Ieſus Chriſte, and thou haſt puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Chriſte whych is the lyfe of my
<pb facs="tcp:1572:29"/>ſoule. the harte of my harte, the ſprite of my ſprite (as Dauid ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth god my fleſhe and my harte,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 73.</note> god of my harte. thou ſhuldeſt, yf my death had not bene inough for my ſinns, turned me into nothing, and letten alone that innocente, and iuſte Chriſte more deare and intier to me then myne owne ſoule wherfore I feele more that, that he ſuffered for me, then I ſhulde haue felte, if I had ſuffered all the tormente poſſible on myne owne body, but well wyſt thou, that I coulde not by reaſon of my frailty, a vyde and ſuffer all, that I had deſerued for my ſynnes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou choſe that my ghty and ſtronge Chriſt to ſuffer for them in my ſteade, and more ouer haſt ſet hym in my harte to thentent that I ſhuld not onely fele that he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, but alſo that he myght geue
<pb facs="tcp:1572:30"/>me ſtrenghth to be able to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Thou mayſt alſo ſay: Lord albe it I haue ſinned, I am regenerate and borne agayne by Chriſt. I am no more the man that ſynned, but I am a new creature: wherfore thou can not iuſtly poniſhe me, by cauſe that ſpryte of myne, that ſynned,
<note place="margin">Gala. ii.</note> is dead, and Chriſt lyueth in me. I lyue no longer my ſelfe, but Chriſt in me. poniſh, kylle, and turne to nought that ſprit of mine, that wyl of myne, ſpoile from me that olde Adam, that ſenſualitie, and al that in me hath ſinned: and poniſhe not me, ſithen by the new ſprite, that I receuid of Chriſt I am hys moſte innocente creatur. more ouer thou Lord haſt geuen me Chriſt wyth al his diuine trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures &amp; graces,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 3.</note> &amp; that to be more ſurely mine, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am my ſelf, and in ſo moch as he is myne entier I
<pb facs="tcp:1572:30"/>am able to ſatiſfy for al my dettes</p>
            <p>What feareſt thou then O ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoule. ſeeſt thou not that, as the blood of Abelcried for ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gance,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo this blood of chriſt callith for mercy and he can not but muſt nedes be herd.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> one abiſſe calleth on another I me ane the bothomeles abiſſe of my ſynnes hath nede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abiſſe of Chriſtes paſſion, and the abiſſe of Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> calleth to the abiſſe of the mercye of god.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſay therfore to Chriſt. O Lord make thy mercy maruelo us and wonderful, thou ſaueſt them that truſte in the: cry ſaue me for thy mercy ſake: take and e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brace thyne the rightwiſnes of Chriſt, &amp; then can I be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented thou ſay.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7.</note> Iudge me lord acording to my ryghtwyſnes. Let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore go to the court of the mercy of god, &amp; if we be called to the barre of iuſtice, let vs apeale all wayes to mercy, and ſee that
<pb facs="tcp:1572:31"/>neuer a man appeare before the throne of iuſtice excepte fyrſt he be clothed wyth Chriſt through faith and then he may be preſented bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delye, as he that is armed wyth innocencye and truth may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented afore any place of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And god ſhall accepte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ryghtwyſe. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be all honour and glory through Ieſu Chriſt oure Lorde. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <head>BY WHAT MEANE <hi>to come to heauen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>EXPERIENCE PROVETH THAT <hi>euerye creature hathe naturallye a deſyre</hi>
               </hi> and appetyte to reſorte to it owne proper place, and manſyon, and namely ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bycauſe he is the moſt ſouereine creature of al other
<pb facs="tcp:1572:31"/>And for ſo moch as ouer natiue cuntrie is not here vpon the earth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebre.</hi> 15. <hi>Colloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 1</note> but in heauen is our place of reſte (conſiderynge that all men haue this deſier to go to heauen) I take yt to be expedyent to weygh and ponder how we may go thither.</p>
            <p>God hath geuen vs Chriſt for an onely mirrour, glaſſe, rule, ſqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, Maiſter, and Guyde: wherfore whoſo is wylling to walke thither I meane to heauen, muſte go the ſame path, that he hath gone and troden before vs, by cauſe he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the waye moſt perfectly, and tawght it to vs withowt any gyle as wel by hys examples, as by his woords, therfore he that ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dith, to go to heauen muſt folow hym. And firſt as he being in the ſhape and fourme of god was not prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, nor an arrogant vſurper, nor aſcribed to hymſelf that he myght
<pb facs="tcp:1572:32"/>conueniently haue done: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wyſe, was louelyhumble, of noreputacion,
<note place="margin">Philip. ii</note> and toke vpon hym the ſhape of a ſeruant, or rather of a ſynner,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> and god layed on him all our wickednes, ye and moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly admited and allowed them for hys owne, as though he had committed them hymſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now in lyke maner, a Chriſten man beynge alredye regenerate and borne agayne by Chryſt, and graffede into hym by a lyuynge fayth. cometh doune from heuen, that is from hys owne pryde, and falſe excellency,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> for (as Chriſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) no man goeth vp in to heuen. but he that cometh doune, that is the ſon of man and hys members. wherfore by &amp; by as a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath aliuely light taſt and &amp; feling of Chriſt, &amp; his great benefite he is hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth him ſelf of no value
<pb facs="tcp:1572:32"/>and nothing in his reputacion. for when he ſeeth by diuine influence, the mekenes of chriſt, his liveralite pacience, loue, goodnes, innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſy, wyth other of his vertues, he is of force conſtrayned to feele his oune pride, vnkindnes, vnpacientnes, wyckednes, vngodlynes, and hys other iniquities. And as god put vpon Chriſt all our ſynnes, and he wyth moſte tender loue receyued them: ſo wyll thys Chriſten man aſcribe to himſelfe al the offences of the world: biraeſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuith, that if god had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drawen from him his grace &amp; had not borne him vp, but miniſtrid to him occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp; oportunitie to offend, thee hadde not bene a ſynne in all the world but he had done it wherfore he wyll attribute to himſelfe all, as th oughe he hadde committed them in deede ſo that all be yt in
<pb facs="tcp:1572:33"/>Chriſt, and by Chriſt he perceueth hym ſelfe innocent and ſafe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtandyng of hymſelfe he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth yt, that he is moſte damned, and greatiſt ſinner of al the world and is forced to ſaye that (which Paul ſpake long ago) Chriſt cam in to the worlde to ſaue ſynners,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1</note> wherof I am one of the chyfe.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde acte of Chryſte was, that, after he was thus hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, clothed wyth our frayle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, borne, and ſhewed forthe to the world, he liued al to gether for hys neyghbour, and ſought onely the glory of hys father, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of hys bretherne, wythowte any regard or reſpect to hymſelfe. (and cauſe why is) for that he was ſo full of loue,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn.</hi> 1.</note> grace, fauour, truth, godlines, and al light, vertue, and perfection, wherfore conſideringe he had no nede to enrych hymſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:33"/>he lyued holy to the welth and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefyte of others,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſen.</hi> 1 <hi>Roma.</hi> 15.</note> as Paule ſayeth Chriſte hath not pleaſed himſelfe he was inflamed in ſoch wyſe with a feruent deſyre to ſaue the world, for the glory of hys father, that he beyng cleane ſwalowed vp in god, had no mynde nor conſyderacion of hym ſelfe. Nowe in ſemblable ſorte that true Chriſten man, that ſeeth himſelfe the ſonne and heyre of god, as Lorde of al ſtudyeth, not to lyue to hys owne vſe, but is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye bente to the benefityng of hys brothern ne for goddes glory, and beynge as it were chaunged into theyr nature feeleth al theyr good, and euyll, as Paule dyd.</p>
            <p>Next enſueth the thyrde acte, that lyke as the worlde perſecuted Chriſte, ſo it purſue hym, and that bycauſe in ſauyng hys neyghbour and ſekynge the glorye of god, he
<pb facs="tcp:1572:34"/>auaunceth and ſet forth the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the goſpel, and the great mercy of god: thruſtyng downe, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng throwyng done to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and makyng nothyng of man: and bycauſe the worlde repyneth at thys, therfore immediatlye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth perſecucyon, in lyke caſe therfore as the hoole life of Chriſt was one continuall perſecucion bycauſe it was godly, ſo chanceth fytely &amp; agreably to a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtien, that magnifyeth the greate benifite, whych we haue receuid by Chriſte. whych thynge is open and manifeſt in ſundry places of the actes of the apoſtles.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 45, 9</note> for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly as the apoſtles had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the goſpell, they were purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo the caſe goethe in thys oure time. More ouer as Chriſte was done on the croſſe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence, he wold not come done, although in
<pb facs="tcp:1572:34"/>ſcorne it was ſayed to hym,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math. xx</hi> 7</note> that yf he were the ſon of god, he ſhuld come doune of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, &amp; they wold beleue hym: but bycauſe he was the ſon of god, he wolde not come doune, but abyde there, &amp; with his oune death make perfecte our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion. in like maner alſo a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be tranſformed and changed in to Chryſte crucyfyed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.</note> ſo that wyth Paule he may ſay I am crucyfed wyth Chryſt, in ſuch wiſe alſo knit to him on the croſſe, that nothynge ys hable to parte me frome the loue of god,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 3.</note> whych is in Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Further more as Chriſt dyed on the croſſe ſo a Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liueth in Chriſt, dyeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world in ſuch ſorte, that he paſſith not of riches, honour, dignitie, kynred, frendes, worldly pleaſures, or proſperitee, conſidering y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſeeth bifaith that
<pb facs="tcp:1572:35"/>he is ſafe, happy, and ſonne, and heyre of god, yea euen as Chriſte was buryed, ſo is he, ſo that the worlde counteth hym not onelye for a thyng deade,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 6.</note> but rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, flyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge and lothſome, wherfore he muſt ſaye wyth Paule,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.</note> the worlde is crucyfyed to me, and I to the worlde. He beſyde thys muſte ryſe with Chriſte in newnes of lyfe, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing after another maner then he dyd before that he was regenerate by Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 6.</note> bicauſe he is become<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual he liueth to the glory of god.</p>
            <p>And thus fynally with chriſt he aſcendeth into heuen ſtanding,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſen.</hi> 3.</note> as touchyng his thoughtes affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and deſyres, aboue in his celeſtiall cuntrey, ſo that he ſay with Paule oure conuerſacyon is in heauen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.</note> wher he enioyeth and taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and comfort in god. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be alwayes al honoure and glory,
<pb facs="tcp:1572:35"/>through Ieſu chriſt our lord. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>HOW GOD HATH SATIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed <hi>for our ſynnes and hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Paradiſe for us.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD BY HYS ABSOLVTE AND <hi>free pouer myght haue ſaued us Wythoute</hi>
               </hi> any ſatiſfaction at all: In as moch as the iuſtice of god is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and pleaſed of al that is lyking his good wil: neuertheleſſe he hath appoynted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſtyng by hys diuine mynde &amp; wiſdome, neuer to ſaue ſinner, oneles firſt he were ful lye ſatiſfied, &amp; ſethen he perceyued that we could not do it our ſelfes, he was minded to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de into the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to make for vs ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; layed on him the iniquities of vs al, as Iſay wrote.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſaye.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And he right louingly, although he were a very innocent, toke them for his owne, and was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to ſatiſfy for our
<pb facs="tcp:1572:36"/>offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, to ſuffer that we had deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, &amp; dye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, according to his fathers wil, as Paul writeth he toke our infirmities for his own and he hath borne oure iniquities and miſeries, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came into the world as though he had ben an offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, he toke a ſymilitude of ſyn to ſerue our turne on the behalfe of our ſinnes &amp; as though we had ben moſt innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 43.</note> &amp; he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted al the ſins on his wil was to go alone to the deth, &amp; therfore he ſayed to his diſciples in the garden: ſtande therin peace,
<note place="margin">Math. xxuii</note> reſt, &amp; without care, &amp; ſuffer me alone to enter into the battaile, &amp; abide on my bones that you haue deſerued. and meting the multitude he ſaied to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeke you:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18.</note> they a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered, Ieſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth as though they ſhuld haue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed, we ſeke for hym, whiche hath vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him all the ſyns of the world. And chriſt made a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer, I am he, I
<pb facs="tcp:1572:36"/>haue taken on me al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes, loue hath layde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on my ſhulders, ther fore if you ſeke for me as a man in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes let my diſciples and my elected paſſe as innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes eaſe, ſatiſfie reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; do your worſt to me, which am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to ſuffer for al one cauſe alſo, wherfore chriſt being accuſed at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeate of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, made no anſwer was to ſhew y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had againſt him all actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in ſomoch as he had embra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced for his owne al our ſynnes. It pleaſed hym alſo to be crowned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thornes, as king of al our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp; ſet betwen tow thefes as the ſtarkeſt errand thefe of al, likewiſe was he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to be ſtrike<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our ſyns, as (Eſay ſayeth) he was ſmyten for our infirmities and broſed for our iniquityes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſaye.</hi> 53.</note> and oſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: god hath chaſtyſed &amp; beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for the ſinnes of his people and
<pb facs="tcp:1572:37"/>by his woundes, and paſſions we be made hole, he payed that he owed not,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alm.</hi> 63.</note> (as Dauid ſaied I haue payed thoſe thynges that I tooke not.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſay.</hi> 43.</note> and Eſay alſo dyd ſaye in the parſon of Chriſt, you haue but me to trouble for your iniquities. he was contented that vppon hym ſhold come al thoſe infamies, ſcla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and rebukes, which we haue deſerued for oure ſynnes, whych thynge Dauid ſingnified in ſpryte in the parſone of Chryſte wher he ſaieth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſalm.</hi> 68.</note> the rebukes, and reproches, wherwyth they ſlandered the, fell all vpon me, yea and thoſe curſes alſo, that were due to vs fell vpon hym, (as Paule ſayeth) he hath redemed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the curſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ala.</hi> 3</note> in that he became a curſt for vs. and lyke a godly ſhepherde hauyng on hys backe the loſt ſhepe (for he hath his kyngedome vppon hys ſhulders)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ay.</hi> 6</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:1572:37"/>hath he borne our ſynnes on the croſſe,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petri. ii.</hi>
               </note> (as Peter ſayeth) he hath borne our ſyns in hys body vppon the croſſe and tre. vpon it as it had bene an altar, to condemne oure ſynnes, wyth the ſynne that was imputed to him, was he offered as a ſacrifiſe to be burned in the fier and fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of gods loue, and to the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Paule writeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ii Corin.</hi> 5.</note> he that knewe no ſynne was made ſynne for vs. it was gods wyll &amp; mynde, that he which was moſte innocent ſhoulde be doone on the croſſe as though he were not onely a ſinner but euen ſyn it ſelfe &amp; thus (as Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niel propheſied was iniquite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) &amp; in one day god toke it oute of the world, acordyng to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſye of zachary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zachar.</hi> 5 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> wherfore ſaynte Iohn ſayeth he appeared to take a way our ſynns, and ſaynt Iohn Baptiſt ſayeth of Chriſt that he is
<pb facs="tcp:1572:38"/>the lambe of god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taketh away the ſynnes of the worlde. Therefore when Chryſt ſuffered moſte louig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye all that, whych we haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebre.</hi> 1</note> he ſatiſfyed for vs, and purged vs from oure ſynnes. he after the maner of the prodygal ſonne, of an excedyng loue, that he bare to the ſowle, when he hadde geuen hys diuine treaſures of grace to the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye open ſynners &amp; harlotes and had taken to hym ſelf our ſynnes, as yf he had done them hym ſelfe, he made prayer to his father that he wolde pardon them to him &amp; to him he pardoned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for we were not worthy: nether wolde he yeld vp his ſprite tyl fyrſt he had bowed doune hys heade that ys vntyll he had moued god,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.</note> which ys (as Paule writeth) his heade to pardone vs to Chryſte therfore were our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aſcribed ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtly he meryted
<pb facs="tcp:1572:38"/>that death for hys ſynnes, not by cauſe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but bicauſe he admited them for his oune and ſo hath he ſatiſfyed for them, not only ſuffycyently, but alſo more then was requiſite. for to god ys one teare of Chriſt more pleaſant, then all the ſynnes of the worlde dyſpleaſant. &amp; that lyfe &amp; death of hys were more to the honoure of god, then our life was to hys dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoure, yea he hath not onelye ſatiſfyed for our ſynnes, but hath purchaced for vs lyfe euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>But happly wylt thou ſay, then nede I to take no paynes nor tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyl to ſatiſfye for my ſyns, nor to deſerue paradiſe, I may take mine eaſe, or do what euyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liketh me geuing me to pleaſur, &amp; good che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are, for if it be as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaieſt, I cannot but be ſaued. I a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer thus. firſt I ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oughteſt not to
<pb facs="tcp:1572:39"/>laboure thy ſelfe for the entente to ſatyſfye for thy ſynnes nor yet to deſerue paradiſe: for that is onely Chriſtes office, nor thou canſt haue any ſuch entent wyth our doyng greate iniury and wronge to god. but where as thou ſayeſte, that thou wold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iue idlye or doo euyll, after that Chriſte hath now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the frome all euill, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the the greatteſt felicitie: I make the anſwer on thys wyſe. If caſe were that one were led to the gallowes for hys rybaldry and noghtines, and his lord or maiſter of mere fauour and good wil ſhuld deliuer hym, and counte hym for hys ſonne, and yet woulde ſaye, my lord or Maiſter hath deliuered me frome all euyll, and taken me for hys ſonne and heyre, the refore wyl I go my way and be idle, and in folowyng myne own luſtes, and
<pb facs="tcp:1572:39"/>wyl do in him wrong: how thynk you, in thys caſe be not theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wordes? euen the lyke ſayeſte thow Chryſte hath delyuered me from hell, and made me the ſonne of god, &amp; heyre of heuen, wherfore I wyll ſtand like an idle parſone, or rather do more euyll, Chriſte certes dyed not for the, nor ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for thy dettes, nor yet merited for the paradiſe to thentent thou ſhulde ſtande idle, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſynne, and become a ſtarke ribalde, but that thou, ſeyng hys greate loue, and hou greatly ſynne diſpleaſed hym ſeeynge he was wyllynge to dye bycauſe to take them oute of the world, ſhulde no more doo ſynne, but honour hym, loue hym, thank hym, put thy truſte in hym, and worke vertuoſe and good workes plentiouſlye, not as a bonde ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to eſcape hell, ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:1572:40"/>delyuered the, ne yet to get para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe, the whych Chryſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for the, but as a naturall ſonne for the glorye of god, moued therto by mocyon of faythe, loue, and ſpryte, not by mannes wyt, ſenſualytie, or thy behofe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modytye. Moreouer eyther thou beleueſt that Chriſt hath ſatiſfyed for the or not, yf thou beleue not, that he hath delyuered the frome hell and gotten the Paradyſe, yf thou be wyſe, thou wylt ſearche to helpe thy ſelf, and ſo wylt thou not be idle, mochleſſe wylt thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt ſinnes: but rather enforce thyſelfe to make ſatyſfaccion for thy ſelfe and to deſerue paradiſe, whych is athyng impoſſible, but yf thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue lyuelye, that he had ſo loued the, that to ſaue the, he dyed on the croſſe, thou ſhulde be conſtrayned to loue hym agayn, and to do for
<pb facs="tcp:1572:40"/>his glory, maruelouſe workes ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſlye and redyly to beleue that we are ſaued by Chriſt maketh not vs negligente and naughtye, but feruent and holye.</p>
            <p>Let vs therfore render tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to oure Lorde god, ſeynge he hath wyth ſo greate loue ſaued vs by ſo hyghe, ryche, happye, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſe meane. To whome be al waye all honour, laude and glorye, throughe Ieſu Chriſt our Lorde. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED <hi>at London by me R. C. for Wyllyam Reddell duellyng at the ſigne of the George in Pouls chyrch yarde.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
